# Alessandro Baccarini

Curriculum Vitae

### **Contact Information**

$\searrow$	Email	abaccarini@proton.me
3	Website	abaccarini.github.io
<b>②</b>	Telegram	alessandro_baccarini
in	LinkedIn	alessandro-baccarini
(7)	GitHub	abaccarini
<b>g</b> i	Scholar	1086 citations, Nov. 2024

# **Research Interests**

My interests span across areas of information security, applied cryptography, and privacy-enhancing technologies. I design and implement protocols for secure multi-party computation (MPC) based on secret sharing for a variety of practical applications, such as privacy-preserving machine learning, sustainability, and outsourcing. Additionally, I research how to quantify information disclosure from arbitrary secure function evaluations through information-theoretic approaches. I am also interested in quantum-resilient cryptographic techniques.

### **Education**

PhD, Computer Science, University at Buffalo	Aug. 2024
Advisor: Marina Blanton	
MS, Cybersecurity, Fordham University	May 2019
Advisor: Thaier Hayajneh	
BS, Physics, Fordham University	May 2017
Minor, Mathematics	

# **Work Experience**

Research/Teaching Assistant, Computer Science University at Buffalo	Jun. 2019 – July 2024
<b>Adjunct Assistant Professor</b> , Physics Fordham University	Aug. 2017 – May 2019
<b>Graduate Research Assistant</b> , Cybersecurity Fordham University	Aug. 2017 – May 2019

## Awards and Recognition

Alan Selman Scholarship, University at Buffalo

Mar. 2024

First place \$2000 cash prize, focus in theoretical computer science.

GSAS Centennial Scholarship, Fordham University

2017 - 2019

Tuition support, stipend for both academic years and summer semesters.

### **Publications**

### **Thesis**

[1] Alessandro Baccarini. New Directions in Secure Multi-Party Computation: Techniques and Information Disclosure Analysis. PhD thesis, University at Buffalo, 2024.

### **Conference Proceedings**

- [2] **Alessandro Baccarini**, Marina Blanton, and Shaofeng Zou. Understanding information disclosure from secure computation output: A study of average salary computation. In *ACM Conference on Data and Application Security and Privacy (CODASPY)*, pages 187–198, 2024.
- [3] **Alessandro Baccarini** and Thaier Hayajneh. Evolution of format preserving encryption on IoT devices: FF1+. In *Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS)*, pages 1628–1637, 2019.
- [4] Abdullah Alhayajneh, **Alessandro Baccarini**, and Thaier Hayajneh. Quality of service analysis of VoIP services. In *IEEE Annual Ubiquitous Computing, Electronics & Mobile Communication Conference (UEMCON)*, pages 812–818, 2018.

#### **Refereed Journals**

- [5] **Alessandro Baccarini**, Marina Blanton, and Shaofeng Zou. Understanding information disclosure from secure computation output: A comprehensive study of average salary computation. *ACM Transactions on Privacy and Security (TOPS)*, 2024, to appear.
- [6] Alessandro Baccarini, Marina Blanton, and Chen Yuan. Multi-party replicated secret sharing over a ring with applications to privacy-preserving machine learning. *Proceedings on Privacy Enhancing Technologies (PoPETs)*, 2023(1):608–626, 2023.
- [7] Abdullah Alhayajneh, **Alessandro Baccarini**, Gary Weiss, Thaier Hayajneh, and Aydin Farajidavar. Biometric authentication and verification for medical cyber physical systems. *Electronics*, 7(12):436, 2018.
- [8] Kristen Griggs, Olya Ossipova, Christopher Kohlios, **Alessandro Baccarini**, Emily Howson, and Thaier Hayajneh. Healthcare blockchain system using smart contracts for secure automated remote patient monitoring. *Journal of Medical Systems*, 42(7):130, 2018.

### **Technical Reports**

[9] **Alessandro Baccarini**, Marina Blanton, and Shaofeng Zou. Understanding information disclosure from secure computation output: A study of average salary computation. arXiv preprint arXiv:2209.10457, 2024.

# **Research Projects**

# MPC and Privacy-Preserving Machine Learning University at Buffalo

2020 - Present Repository

- Designed a comprehensive ring-based framework of replicated secret sharing multi-party protocols for an arbitrary number of parties in the semi-honest (passively secure), honest majority setting.
- Implemented protocol constructions in C++ and extensively benchmarked our framework, obtaining an up to 33× performance gain over existing state-of-the-art secret sharing techniques.
- Applied techniques to privacy-preserving machine learning tasks, including (quantized) neural network inference and support vector machine classification.
- Discovered an algebraic optimization for secure quantized neural network inference that significantly improved efficiency and led to an over 2× improvement over prior works.

### **PICCO Compiler**

2022 - Present Repository

University at Buffalo

- Core developer and maintainer of *PICCO*, a source-to-source compiler used to translate general-purpose programs into their secure implementations for deployment in a distributed setting.
- Extensively optimized existing field-based protocol implementations, while simultaneously performing a large-scale refactor to improve future maintainability and support extensibility to stronger security settings.
- Integrated ring-based protocol constructions into the compiler to support general-purpose computation over integer and floating-point inputs.
- Mentored two REU students tasked with optimizing the compiler's networking functionalities, along
  with developing a web interface for entering private inputs and retrieving outputs of secure computation.

# **Disclosure Analysis from Secure Function Evaluation** University at Buffalo

2021 - Present Repository

- Designed a novel information-theoretic approach for evaluating the information disclosure about private inputs from the output of secure function evaluations.
- Comprehensively analyzed a practically significant statistical function (the average salary) through extensive theoretical and analytical analysis in a variety of computational configurations.
- Applied our framework to complex descriptive statistical functions in conjunction with data-driven techniques to measure information disclosure.

### **Blockchain Applications in Healthcare**

2017 - 2019

Fordham University

- Led the design of one of the first frameworks that fused blockchain and healthcare into a HIPAA-compliant IoT remote patient monitoring system, based on the Ethereum protocol.
- Assisted in prototype smart contract development in Solidity to support real-time automated monitoring.

## Significant Course Projects

### Implementation of the Apple PSI System

University at Buffalo, Security and Privacy in IoT

Repository

2021

- Developed a modified variant of Apple's private set intersection (PSI) system in Python to obliviously detect harmful media within a database through neural network-based perceptual hash functions.
- Implemented various necessary cryptographic primitives to build the framework, including secret sharing of private keys, HMAC key derivation and pseudorandom functions, and Diffie-Hellman group construction.

### **Quantum Secret Sharing of Classical Information**

2020

University at Buffalo, Applied Cryptography and Computer Security

Repository

• Analyzed the Hillery-Buek-Berthiaume quantum secret sharing protocol of classical information, and implemented the construction in IBM's Python Qiskit framework.

### **Professional Service**

#### **Conference Committees**

USENIX Security Symposium, artifact evaluation committee member	2024
USENIX Security Symposium, artifact evaluation committee member	2023

### **Conference and Journal Refereeing**

IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics and Security (TIFS)
IEEE Transactions on Dependable and Secure Computing (TDSC)
European Symposium on Research in Computer Security (ESORICS)
IEEE/ACM International Conference on Automated Software Engineering (ASE)
Multidisciplinary Digital Publishing Institute (MDPI) Entropy, Sensors, Symmetry, Information Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS)

### Technical Skills

**Cryptographic** secure multi-party computation, secret sharing, differential privacy, homomorphic encryption, signatures and commitments, zero-knowledge proofs

**Languages** C/C++, Python, Bash, Lua, Solidity, LATEX

**Developer** Git, SVN, CMake, GDB, Neovim, VS Code, Unix

Libraries GMP, GMPFR, GSL, OpenSSL, NumPy, Matplotlib, TensorFlow

# **Teaching**

# At the **University at Buffalo**:

CSE 116 Computer science II (Instructor)	2 semesters
CSE 4/529 Algorithms for Modern Computing Systems (TA)	3 semesters
CSE 4/531 Analysis of Algorithms (TA)	1 semester
CSE 542 Software Engineering Concepts (TA)	1 semester

# At Fordham University:

PHYS 1511/12 Physics I/II Lab (Instructor) 4 semesters